In the last lecture, we created our first nextjs application.
Son derste ilk nextjs uygulamasn oluturduk.
Now this is not a complete nextjs course and you could actually create a course about this,
imdi bu tam bir sonraki ders deil ve aslnda bu konuda bir kurs
I just want to show you the bare basic features so that you can dive deeper,
oluturabilirsin, sadece size plak temel zellikleri gstermek istiyorum, bylece daha derine
for example with the github repo I pointed you to.
dalmak, rnein seni iaret ettiim github repo ile.
So let's now see how we can easily navigate from our main index page to the auth index page,
imdi ana dizin sayfamzdan auth indeks sayfasna nasl kolayca gidebileceimizi
for that we of course need a link and with react router, we use the linked component react router
grelim, bunun iin elbette bir balantya ve tepki veren bir
gave us. Now with nextjs,
ynlendiriciye ihtiyacmz var. imdi nextjs ile
we also have a link component we can use,
birlikte kullanabileceimiz bir balant
it's not coming from react router though
bileenimiz var, tepki veren
but instead it's coming from well, nextjs of course.
ynlendiriciden gelmiyor ama bunun yerine elbette gelecekten geliyoruz.
So to navigate around, I'll import a new component,
Bu yzden, etrafta gezinmek iin, yeni bir bileeni,
the link component from next/link, important link has a lower case L here in the import path.
balant bileenini bir sonraki / balantdan ie aktaracam, nemli balantnn, ie aktarm yolunda burada kk bir harf L var.
Now we can add such a link here,
imdi buraya byle bir
for example, I can add a paragraph in my main page and say go to and now link auth.
link ekleyebiliriz, rnein ana sayfama para ekleyebilirim ve imdi auth'a gidip balant kurabilirim.
Now for this to work, the link of course needs to be configured to point somewhere and you do this with
imdi bunun almas iin, elbette ki balantnn bir yere iaret edecek ekilde yaplandrlmas gerekiyor ve
the ref attribute like on a normal anchor tag in normal html.
bunu normal html'deki normal bir balant etiketindeki gibi ref znitelii ile yapyorsunuz.
And there, you can point to auth/auth to point to the auth folder and there, it will always pick the index.js
Ve orada, auth / auth'a, auth klasrne iaret etmek iin iaret edebilir ve orada her zaman dizini seer. Eer varsa,
file if you got one.
js dosyas.
So link alone won't do the trick though,
Yalnz balant sadece hile yapmaz, aslnda
you actually still use the normal anchor tag inside of it without the ref attribute though, behind the
hala normal balant etiketini ref znitelii olmadan kullanrsnz, ancak sahnelerin arkasnda, nextjs temel
scenes, nextjs will basically add the ref attribute to the anchor tag but then capture any clicks
olarak ref zniteliini anchor etiketine ekleyecektir ancak daha sonra herhangi bir tklamay yakalayacaktr. etiketini
on the anchor tag and handle that internally so that you don't really reload the page.
tutturun ve dahili olarak ileyin, bylece sayfay gerekten yeniden yklemeyin.
If we now save this and go back to our application, let's reload the app,
imdi bunu kaydedip uygulamamza geri dnersek, uygulamay yeniden
we should see the link down, if we click on it, we go to /auth.
ykleyelim, balanty grmeliyiz, eer tklarsak, / auth'a gideriz.
Another cool thing you should be able to see is if you go to the network tab and reload your main
Grebilmeniz gereken bir baka gzel ey, a sekmesine gidip ana
page and you click on auth,
sayfanza gidip auth'a tklarsanz, ekstra
you also see that an extra auth bundle was loaded and that is what nextjs does for you,
bir auth paketinin yklendiini ve nextJs'in sizin iin ne yaptn, otomatik kod blme
automatic code splitting.
olduunu grrsnz. .
By the way, don't be intimidated by the file sizes,
Bu arada, dosya boyutlar tarafndan gz
this is not optimized at all,
korkutmayn, bu hi
this contains a lot of development environment overhead.
optimize edilmez, bu bir ok gelitirme ortam ierir.
So that's the automated code splitting you get for free and with the link you see here, you can easily
Yani, cretsiz olarak alabileceiniz otomatik kod budur ve burada grdnz
navigate around in your application.
balant sayesinde, uygulamanzda kolayca gezinebilirsiniz.
So that's how we use the link and that is how we can easily get around in our application.
te bu yzden balanty kullanyoruz ve bu bizim uygulamamzla kolayca nasl baa kabiliyoruz.
Here also not limited to using the link though,
Ayrca, balanty kullanmakla da snrl kalmyoruz,
let's say you have a button where you want to go to auth and you want to do this on a click and therefore
hadi gidip auth'a gitmek istediiniz bir dmeniz olduunu ve bunu bir tklamayla yapmak istediinizi ve bu
navigate imperatively,
nedenle de zorunlu
so in your code then you can always do this.
olarak gezinebildiinizi diyelim, bylece kodunuzda her zaman bunu yapabilirsiniz.
For example here of course by registering onClick listener and then defining a method which should get
rnein, elbette, onClick dinleyicisine kayt yaptrmak ve daha sonra, bir snf temel bileeniniz
executed and that of course could be if you have a class based component,
varsa, bu bileenin herhangi bir yntemine sahipseniz, yrtlmesi gereken bir yntem
any method in that component, here I'm just writing it in inline to keep it brief. You then can import the
tanmlamak ve bunu burada tutmak iin satr ii yazyorum. ksa. Daha sonra ynlendiriciyi bir sonraki / ynlendiriciden
router from next/router, like this with lowercase r though and then here, you can simply call router
alabilirsin, bunun gibi kk harfle r ve sonra burada sadece ynlendirici push / auth'u arabilirsin
push/auth
ve bu ok hzl
and this is a very quick way of imperatively
bir ekilde kodun iinde,
so in code, navigating around. If you now go back and load your main page, got that button, if you click it, you're
etrafta gezinmek iin ok hzl bir yoldur. imdi geri dnp ana sayfanz yklerseniz, o dmeyi
on the auth page now navigated through code with that router object.
aldnz, eer tklatrsanz, imdi o ynlendirici nesnesinde kod araclyla gezinilen yetkilendirme sayfasndasnz.
This is how you get around, how you use the link in nextjs.
Bu nasl olurda olsun, nextjs'deki balanty nasl kullanrsn.
One of the core concepts and it looks super simple but a lot is happening behind the scenes,
Temel kavramlardan biri ve sper basit grnyor ama sahnelerin ardnda ok ey
most importantly the automatic code splitting which is awesome.
oluyor, en nemlisi de harika olan otomatik kod blme.
Now let's see what else nextjs gives us and how we work with it.
imdi nextJs'in bize ne verdiini ve onunla nasl altmz grelim.